Hi and welcome back to another episode
of It's Dr. Dan and today we're going to
be learning how to name acids and bases.
Now the tricky part about naming acids
is which we'll start with first is
trying to identify what type of acid it
is which has to do with what kind of
ionic compound it is. So the first type
is a binary acid. So when you hear the
word binary or by that means that
there's two different species that we're
going to be seeing. So two elements that
we will have in one of these things. So
every acid to write it is always going
to start with hydrogen which is going to
be one of our species followed by
typically some type of H hallogen or a
sulfur uh ion afterwards. So if we were
to go through this, how would we what
would be an example of that? So let's
say if I had hydrogen and florine
bonding together, how would I name this
acid? So we can see that a hydrogen is
out front. So this designates that this
is an acid. So H is first when we're
writing acids. So we see that there's
two species. So one of them is hydrogen.
The other one is florine here. So as our
two different things that we are showing
here. In order to name it, the first
thing we're going to do is for hydrogen,
we're going to write hydro.
And being that it is an acid, it's going
to have a different ending. So we have
florine, which is our
element here. But what we're going to
do, we're only going to keep the first
syllable. So we're going to keep floor.
So it's floor and then in. So that
ending part is going to be dropped as a
result and that's going to be replaced
with ic acid. So when we write that down
again, it's going to be hydro floor and
we're going to be replacing the ending
with ic acid. So with this, right, just
to kind of show off that entire naming
here. So we have hydro and icic acid are
the parts that we got to write for any
of these different structures. So if we
were going to do another one for example
what if I gave you HBr.
If we see this one well once again we
have those two species here. So we have
hydrogen as one bromine is the second
one. So once again this is going to
start with hydro to represent the
hydrogen. Then being that we have
bromine. So broine
we're going to keep the beginning so be
hydro so it be bro
and then we're going to change the
ending to iick acid so broine right so
bromic acid so hydro bromic acid now if
we wanted to go the other way we could
do that too let's say if I gave you the
following name and I said we had hydro
chloric
acid what would be the name here. Well,
we know that's always going to start
with hydrogen. And then we got to then
try to see is all right. Well, what
about the non-metal that is in this
name? So, if we kind of break down and
see that first syllable here, so what's
chlor? Well, thinking about our
elements, chlorine.
So, this is going to be H.
Now keep in mind when we're balancing
all these hydrogen as an ion being that
we have we have these are things that
are have ionic charges to them. Even
though these are different non-metals
they are considered to be ions. So these
are H+ and HF. So it has a minus and
plus and minus. So we got to keep in
mind that that hydrogen has a plus
charge. So we got to balance that with
swap drop and whenever we have that
given example. Now what other types of
things we might have? We also have oxy
acids. So an oxy acid is any of the
different polyatomics.
So if I have for example uh CO3 2 minus,
this is carbonate. Carbonate is one of
our polyatomics. So if we ever see
anything with the 8 or ending, they can
also combine with different acids. So
the way that we can remember the name
change is there's stupid little
pneumonics that always help us remember.
So for eights I like to remember I hate
this pneumonic. So for those of you who
hate pneumonics, well think of I hate
this pneumonic and that will tell you
how to change the name. So if we have
CO3 2 minus, well how many hydrogens do
we need for that structure to make it an
acid? Well, if every H is a plus and we
have CO3 2 minus, that means we need two
hydrogens. So, this would be H2 CO3 2
minus. So, how would I name it? Well, if
we have carbonate, we keep the element
part of the name. So, we just get rid of
the E ending. So, in this case, it's
going to be carbonic
acid would be its name.
versus let's say if I did something that
was an it. Well, if I had uh SO2
uh 3 minus or sorry 2 minus in this case
or sorry SO3 2 minus
and I wanted to show what is that name.
So this is an it species. So in this
case we would once again try to balance
the 2 minus. So we would need two
hydrogens to balance that. So we'd add
an H2 there. And then how would that
name be? Well, we're going to replace
the it ending of sulfite
with us. So in that case, it's going to
be sulfus
acid. So we still have that acid part of
the name when we go through that. So
let's just quickly summarize. So there's
a bunch of little rules here that I
wrote down. so that way you can have
them for yourself when you're going
through these. And they all revolve
around the polyatomics except for rule
number five which is about binary which
was the first thing we talked about. So
two and three are about eight and I
which we're changing the different
endings. So an eight becomes acid it
becomes acid. Now, when you're going
through any of these different little um
uh these polyatomics, there are some
prefixes that do sometimes go with them.
So, for example, if you have a per or
eight ending with a per prefix and eight
suffix, that would become peric acid.
So, I tried to color code everything for
how we can remember them. So why don't
we try going through a little exercise
trying to name all of the following
ions. So if I have Cl2
minus CL3 minus CL4 minus.
So with these what are all their
endings? Well if you kind of remember
from polyatomics these two in the middle
are chlorate
and chlorite.
If we have one more oxygen, that would
make that perch chlorate.
And then when we have one less oxygen,
this is hypo
chlorite.
Now, if I wanted to make these all
acids, how would I go about doing that?
Well, they all have a negative one
charge. So, how many protons or
hydrogens do I need to balance that out?
Well, each one of them is going to need
one H+
to balance all of these different
species out. So, if I want to break that
down, we'd have H C minus, Cl2 minus,
Cl3 minus, and so on. Now, how do we go
about naming them? Well, if we have a
hypocchlorite, that was rule number or
hypocchlorite,
that was a rule number four here. So in
order to do rule number four, what that
says is we keep the prefix. So it's
going to be hypo.
Then being that it's we're talking about
it's a chlorite. So it's going to become
hypocchloric
acid.
Right? So using rule number four. Then a
chlorite which is going to be using rule
number three.
kind of going a little backwards here um
with all of these. So with three, what
we're going to be doing is chlorite,
that's going to become chlorus acid. So
it's going to become chlorus
acid because we're dropping the it
ending. We're dropping the it ending and
we're keeping hypo for that first one.
So why don't I cross these out? So this
skin dropped that skin dropped. We're
keeping this. Same thing for eight,
right? We're dropping the eight ending
and then it's going from eight to iick.
So remember, I hate this pneumonic. So
we're going from uh we're going from to
chloric acid.
Now for perchlor 8, what are we going to
do there? We're going to keep the purr,
drop the eight, and this is going to
become perchloric acid for its name. So
per chloric
acid.
All right. So notice how we're keeping
with all these different species, we're
keeping that chlor is staying for all of
them when you are writing the different
names. The big thing that is changing is
that we're putting in all of these
little endings here, right? So the
endings are changing, which I'm
highlighting here in green. Uh the
endings change sometimes. So we might
keep a prefix from before. So uh just to
kind of maybe we'll show that here as
well. So like the hypo and perr they're
staying the same because they were in
the original naming.
Okay. So that is a summary of acids.
What about bases? Bases are actually a
little bit easier to name, believe it or
not. The way that bases work is what we
are looking for is a hydroxide. So
there's a hydroxide polyatomic. Now what
was the charge for a hydroxide? Well, O
this entire polyatomic is O minus. Now
in order for it to make a base is
typically bonding to some type of cation
ion. So we're going to have a cation ion
bonded to a hydroxide. And a lot of the
times these are in the form of alkali
and alkaline earth metals
which is your first two columns of the
periodic table. So column one and two is
for most examples. That's not all the
time but that is for most of the times
for introductory chemistry we tend to
see alkali alkaline earth metals
attached to hy to a hydroxide. So, if I
show you uh the following, well, I have
Na, which is one of our alkaline metals,
sodium, and that's attached to a
hydroxide. How would you go about naming
it? Well, quite simple. We write out the
metal
followed by hydroxide.
So, we don't actually change anything
about the name, which is kind of nice.
So, if I have sodium,
this would be sodium hydroxide.
And we don't worry about writing any
prefixes or anything else. Uh the only
thing we have to worry about is charges.
So being that we know sodium is a plus
one, hydroxide is a negative one. That's
not too bad at all. Let's try a
different one. What if I gave you
barerium uh hydroxide? How would I
and hydroxide? How would I go through
naming it? Well, how would I name and
balance it? Well, barium is a two plus
charge.
Hydroxide is a minus1 charge. So we're
going to swap drop. Now keep in mind
that two is going to be on the outside
of parentheses. So this is going to
become barerium and the O is one
polyatomic with a two outside of it. So
why don't we show that in red just to
match what we had before. So when we
name that it's going to be barium
hydroxide as the name.
So it's not too bad when we come to
naming. The hardest part is just making
sure you balance it. So hydroxide is
always in the end. If you see that, that
indicates a base. So hydroxides
indicate bases.
All right? So hydrogens in the front
indicate acids. Hydroxides in the back
indicate bases. And I hope that this
video helped you. If you need any future
videos, please like and comment or
subscribe and let me know in the future.
I hope this helped and I'll see you all
later. Thank you. This has been Dr. Dan.
[Music]